Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. Emily Dickinson letters to Josiah Gilbert Holland and Elizabeth Chapin Holland, ca. 1853-1886 (MS Am 1118.2): Guide.
Emily Dickinson letters to Josiah Gilbert Holland and Elizabeth Chapin Holland,
ca. 1853-1886.
Houghton Library, Harvard College Library, Harvard University
MS Am 1118.2
Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886.
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Letters and poems by the American poet Emily Dickinson sent to her friends, Mr. and Mrs. Josiah Holland.
49M-248, 54M-116. Gift of Mrs. Theodora V. W. Ward, 32 Healey Street, Cambridge 38, Mass.; received: 1950 June 8.
Access to the originals requires the permission of the curator.
Readers are expected to use the facsimiles available.
Dickinson was an American poet. Josiah Gilbert Holland, assistant of Samuel Bowles of the Springfield Republican, and his wife Elizabeth were family friends.
Arranged chronologically.
Typescript copies of letters, frequently accompanied by her poems, to Dr. and Mrs. Josiah Holland.
References included in the notes include:
F = Franklin, R. W. The poems of Emily Dickinson. Cambridge, Mass.: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1998.
J = Johnson, Thomas, ed. The complete poems of Emily Dickinson: including variant readings critically compared with all known manuscripts. Cambridge, Mass.: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1955.
JL = Johnson, Thomas, ed. The letters of Emily Dickinson. Cambridge, Mass.: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1958.
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [Josiah Gilbert] Holland,; [Elizabeth (Chapin)] Holland, and "Minnie" [i.e. Amelia (Chapin) May]; [Amherst, autumn 1853?], (1); 2s. (2p.) (Box 2)
  Available to users with a valid Harvard ID.
  JL 133
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst] 2 Jan [1854], (2); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 149
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, winter 1854-1855], (3); 2s. (2p.) (Box 2)
  With this is a T. MS. (copy) poem beginning: Truth is as old as God.
  J 847, Fr 795
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [Elizabeth (Chapin)] Holland,; [Josiah Gilbert] Holland, and "Minnie" [i.e. Amelia (Chapin) May]; Philadelphia [May 1854], (4); 2s. (2p.) (Box 2)
  JL 179
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [Elizabeth (Chapin)] Holland; [Amherst, Sept 1854], (5); 2s. (2p.) (Box 2)
  JL 174
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [Josiah Gilbert] Holland; [Amherst, Nov 1854], (6); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 181
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [Elizabeth (Chapin)] Holland; [Amherst, 20? Jan 1856], (7); 2s. (2p.) (Box 2)
  JL 182
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to same; [Amherst, summer 1856?], (8); 2s. (2p.) (Box 2)
  JL 185
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [Josiah Gilbert] Holland and [Elizabeth (Chapin)] Holland; [Amherst, Nov 1858], (9); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 195
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [Elizabeth (Chapin)] Holland; [Amherst, Mar 1859], (10); 2s. (2p.) (Box 2)
  JL 202
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [Josiah Gilbert] Holland and [Elizabeth (Chapin)] Holland; [Amherst, summer 1859?], (11); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 269
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [Josiah Gilbert] Holland and [Elizabeth (Chapin)] Holland; [Amherst, Sept 1859], (12); 2s. (2p.) (Box 2)
  JL 207
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [Elizabeth (Chapin)] Holland; [Amherst, 8? Dec 1859], (13); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 210
- Dickinson, Lavinia, 1833-1899. A.L.s. to same; [Amherst, Dec 1859], (14); 1s. (3p.) (Box 1)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [ ]; [Amherst, Dec 1859?], (15); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 211
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, Mar 1860], (16); 1s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 204, HCL (H16)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, 1860], (17); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 227
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. Baffled for just a day or two [first line] A.MS.s.; [Amherst, 1860], (17a); 1s. (3p.) (Box 1)
  With rose-bud attached.
  J 110, Fr 66
  Bequest of Theodora V. W. Ward, 1974. [Note: This one manuscript was to remain the property of Mrs. Theodora V. W. Ward during her lifetime, and was merely on deposit in the Library. At her death it become the property of the Library].
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886] [2 poems: Away from home are some and I, [first line] and: Though my destiny be fustian [first line]] TS. (copy); [Boston? and Amherst? ca. 1860-1869?], (17b); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  J 865, Fr 807; J 123, Fr 131
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, early Nov 1865], (18); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 311
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886] T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, late 1865?], (19); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  Includes poem beginning: Not all die early, dying young.
  J 867, Fr 937
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, Mar 1866], (20); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 315
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, early May 1866], (21); 2s. (2p.) (Box 2)
  Includes a T.MS (copy) poem beginning: Count not that far that can be had.
  J 1185, Fr 1124
- Dickinson, Lavinia, 1833-1899. A.L.s. to [Josiah Gilbert Holland and Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, ca. 1866], (22); 1s. (1p.) (Box 1)
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886] T.L. (copy) to [Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, ca. 1867], (23); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 321
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Oct 1870], (24); 2s. (6p.) (Box 1)
  Includes poem beginning: The life we have is very great.
  L354, HCL (H24), J 1168, Fr 1178
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886] A.L. (unsigned) to [same?]; [Amherst, 1870?], (25); 1s. (1p.) (Box 1)
  JL 351 HCL (H25)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, spring 1871], (26); 1s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 359 HCL (H26)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, late Nov 1871], (27); 1s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 369 HCL (H27)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, 1872], (28); 1s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 370 HCL (H28)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Aug 1872], (29); 1s. (3p.) (Box 1)
  JL 377 HCL (H29)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, early summer 1873], (30); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  Includes a T. MS. (copy) poem beginning: The most triumphant Bird.
  J 1283, Fr 1285
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Sep? 1873], (31); 1s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL395 HCL (H31)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, autumn 1873], (32); 1s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 399 HCL (H32)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. Longing is like the seed [first line] A.MS.s.; [Amherst, 1873], (32a); 1s. (2p.) (Box 1)
  J 1350, Fr 1298
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, May 1874], (33); 2s. (6p.) (Box 1)
  JL 412, HCL (H33)
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886] When memory is full [first line] A.MS. (unsigned); [Amherst, 1874], (33a); 1s. (1p.); J 1228, Fr 1301 (Box 1)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, late Jan 1875], (34); 2s. (8p.) (Box 1)
  JL 432, HCL (H34)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, 1875], (35); 1s. (2p.) (Box 1)
  L439, HCL (H35); p. 3: J1336, Fr1371
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. [2 poems: Summer laid her simple hat [first line] and: She laid her docile crescent down [first line]] A.MSS.s.; [Amherst, 1875], (35a); 2s. (3p.) (Box 1)
  J 1421, Fr 1411; J 1514, Fr 1453
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [Elizabeth (Chapin)] Holland; [Amherst, 1876], (36); 1s. (3p.) (Box 1)
  JL 475, HCL (H36)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. No passenger was known to flee [first line] A.MS.s.; [Amherst, 1876], (36a); 1s. (3p.) (Box 1)
  J 1475, Fr 1451
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886] T.L. (copy) to [Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, Aug 1876], (37); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 473
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, winter 1876-1877], (38); 2s. (5p.) (Box 1)
  JL 487, HCL (H38)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, winter 1876-1877], (39); 1s. (3p.) (Box 1)
  Includes poem beginning: "Tomorrow," whose location.
  JL 490, HCL (H39); J1440, Fr1417
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886] A.L. (unsigned) to [same]; [Amherst, winter 1876-1877], (40); 1s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 481, HCL (H40)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, early spring 1877], (41); 2s. (6p.) (Box 1)
  JL 492, HCL (H41)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, late May 1877], (42); 2s. (6p.) (Box 1)
  Includes poem beginning: Bees are Black with Gilt Surcingles.
  JL502, HCL (H42); p. 5-6: J 1444, Fr 1426
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886] A.L. (unsigned) to [same]; [Amherst, early autumn 1877], (43); 1s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 521, HCL (H43)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, early Jan 1878], (44); 2s. (5p.) (Box 1)
  JL 525, HCL (H44)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, early 1878], (45); 2s. (6p.) (Box 1)
  JL 542, HCL (H45)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [Josiah Gilbert Holland]; [Amherst, early 1878], (46); 1s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  Includes poem beginning: These held their Wick above the west.
  JL 544, HCL (H46); p. 3-4: J 1365, Fr 1416
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, Mar 1878], (47); 1s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 547, HCL (H47)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, spring 1878], (48); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 555, HCL (H49)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Jun 1878], (49); 2s. (6p.) (Box 1)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, mid-Jan 1879], (50); 2s. (3p.) (Box 1)
  JL 589, HCL (H50)
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886] A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Oct 1879?], (51); 3s. (6p.) (Box 1)
  JL 619, HCL (H51)
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886] A.L. (unsigned) to [same]; [Amherst] 4, 15 Jul [1880], (52); 3s. (6p.) (Box 1)
  Includes poem beginning: The Road to Paradise is plain.
  JL 650, HCL (H52): p.5, 7: J1571, Fr1525
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Sep 1880], (53); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 667, HCL (H53)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, 5? Dec 1880], (54); 3s. (5p.) (Box 1)
  JL 678, HCL (H54)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, 28 Dec 1880], (55); 2s. (3p.) (Box 1)
  JL 683, HCL (H55)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Jan 1881], (56); 2s. (5p.) (Box 1)
  JL 685, HCL (H56)
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886] A.L. (unsigned) to [same]; [Amherst, 1881], (57); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 687, HCL (H57)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [Josiah Gilbert Holland]; [Amherst, early 1881], (58); 2s. (3p.) (Box 1)
  JL 715, HCL (H58)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, late Mar 1881], (59); 3s. (5p.) (Box 1)
  Color digital facsimile available to users with a valid Harvard ID.
  Includes poem beginning: An Antiquated tree.
  J 1514, Fr 1544
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886] A.L. (unsigned) to [Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, spring 1881], (60); 3s. (5p.) (Box 1)
  JL 692, HCL (H60)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Aug 1881], (61); 3s. (5p.) (Box 1)
  JL 721, HCL (H61)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, late summer 1881], (62); 3s. (5p.) (Box 1)
  JL 723, HCL (H62)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, 13? Oct 1881], (63); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 729
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, 15? Oct 1881], (64); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 730
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, 20 Oct 1881], (65); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 731
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, late Oct 1881], (66); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 732
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, late Oct 1881], (67); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  Includes poem beginning: No Autumn's intercepting Chill.
  JL 738, HCL (H67); p. 7: J 1611, Fr 1563
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, mid-Dec 1881], (68); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 740
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, Christmas 1881], (69); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  Includes a T. MS. (copy) poem beginning: How much of Source escapes with thee--.
  J 1623, Fr 1567
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, late 1881?], (70); 1s. (2p.) (Box 1)
  Includes a portion of the poem, The Things that never can come back, are several, beginning: Foretold Locations--.
  JL 733, HCL (H70); J 1515, Fr 1564
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, 29? Oct 1882], (71); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 775, HCL (H71)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, mid-Nov 1882], (72); 3s. (5p.) (Box 1)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, 19? Dec 1882], (73); 3s. (5p.) (Box 1)
  JL792, HCL (H73)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, after Christmas 1882], (74); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 794, HCL (H74)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, early 1883], (75); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 801, HCL (H75)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, early 1883], (76); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  Includes poem beginning: To see her is a picture--.
  JL 802, HCL (H76); p. 7: J 1631, Fr 1597
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, 3 Mar 1883], (77); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  Includes poem beginning: The Clock strikes one that just struck two--.
  JL 805, HCL (H77); p. 3: J 1640, Fr 1598
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Mar 1883], (78); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 806, HCL (H78)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Mar 1883], (79); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  Includes poem beginning: Forever honored be the tree.
  JL 808, HCL (H79); p. 5, 7: J 1663, Fr 1600
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, spring 1883], (80); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 820, HCL (H80)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, early May 1883], (81); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 822, HCL (H81)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, late Sep 1883], (82); 3s. (5p.) (Box 1)
  JL 866, HCL (H82)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Nov? 1883], (83); 3s. (5p.) (Box 1)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, early 1884], (84); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 882, HCL (H84)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Feb? 1884], (85); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 888, HCL (H85)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Mar 1884], (86); 3s. (6p.) (Box 1)
  Includes 2 poems: (1) Quite empty, quite at rest [first line] and (2) Within that little Hive [first line].
  JL890, HCL (H86); p. 5, 7,: J 1653, Fr 1632; p. 11: J 1654, Fr 1633
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886] A.L. (unsigned) to [same]; [Amherst, 1 Jun 1884], (87); 3s. (5p.) (Box 1)
  JL 901, HCL (H87)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [Theodore Holland]; [Amherst, summer? 1884], (88); 1s. (2p.) (Box 1)
  JL 921, HCL (H88)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, summer 1884], (89); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [Elizabeth (Chapin) Holland]; [Amherst, late Sep 1884], (90); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 936, HCL (H90)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, late Oct 1884], (91); 3s. (5p.) (Box 1)
  JL 950, HCL (H91)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Feb 1885], (92); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
  JL 966, HCL (H92)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, Mar 1885], (93); 2s. (3p.) (Box 1)
  JL 977, HCL (H93)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to [same]; [Amherst, spring 1885], (94); 2s. (4p.) (Box 1)
- [Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886.] T.L. (copy) to [same]; [Amherst, Mar? 1886], (95); 1s. (1p.) (Box 2)
  JL 979, HCL (H94)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. A.L.s. to Josiah Gilbert Holland; [Amherst, Mar. 1886], (96); 2s. (5p.) (Box 1)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. At half past three ... [first line] A.MS.s.; [Amherst, n.d.], (97); 1s. (3p.) (Box 1)
  J 1107, Fr 1099
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. Not all die early, ... [first line] A.MS.s.; [Amherst, n.d.], (98); 1s. (3p.) (Box 1)
- Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886. Truth is as old as God. [first line] A.MS.s.; [Amherst, n.d.], (99); 1s. (3p.) (Box 1)